Guide to the Deutsches Raketen- und Raumfahrt Museum e. V. Records, 1942-1969
Department of Special Collections
Deutsches Raketen- und Raumfahrt Museum e. V. Records,
1942-1969
M0718
Deutsches Raketen- und Raumfahrt Museum e. V.
4.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The collection includes correspondence, essays, financial records, official reports, designs and other illustrations. Also included are papers concerning the earlier Gesellschaft für Weltraumforschung as well as personal papers of Alfred Fritz dating from the late 1940s.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1994
Historical Note
The collection includes papers and illustrations concerning the planned Deutsches Raketen- und Raumfahrtmuseum e.V. The museum was intended to gather and display technical and literary materials (both historical and contemporary) relevent to studies in astronautics. It was also intended to promote such studies through educational programs on both the contemporary state of rocket-technology and the early stages of space travel. The attempt to establish a permanent museum in Stuttgart extended from 1954 to the early 1960's. The museum was to have been an outgrowth of the Gesellschaft fur Weltraumforschung, founded in Stuttgart in 1948. Both the museum and its predecessor were members of the International Astroautical Federation. Among the museum's holdings were an A-4 rocket (v-2), the rocket chamber and gas chamber of the "Veronique," a nose cone and instrumentation of an "Äerobee," as well as post-war technical, scientific, and rocket-related literature by Stoelzel, Mohr, the Deutsche Raketengesellschaft für Raketentechnik und Raumfahrt. During the late 1950's and the early 1960's the museum held at least 12 exhibitions. The museum also cooperated with Columbia-Morningside in the filming of the Wernher von Braun Story.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
The collection primarily conains correspondence conducted worldwide concerning the planned museum. Almost all correspondence involves Alfred Fritz, the museum's founder, managing director, and preeminent figure. The correspondence concerns such matters as conference and membership in various space- and rocket- societies. Other materials include essays, financial records, handwritten manuscripts, and official reports, designs, and illustrations. Also included are papers concerning the earlier Gesellschaft für Weltraumforschung as well as handwritten manuscripts and other personal effects of Alfred Fritz dating from the early 1940's. The collection is of value to those interested in the reception and development of post-war German research in space-travel.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Fritz, Alfred.; American Astronautical Society.; American Rocket Society.; Arbeitsgemeinschaft fèur Raumfahrtforschung.; Bell Aircraft Corporation/Bell Aerosystems Company.; British Interplanetary Society.; Forschungsinstitut fèur Physik der Strahlantriebe.; International Astronautical Federation.; The Glenn L. Martin Company.; von Karman Institute for Fluid Dynamics.; Wissenschaftliche Gesellschaft fèur Luft und Raumfahrt.; Aeronautics.; Rocketry.; Science--History--Germany.; Space ships.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Institutional Correspondence, ca. 1955-1965
  - American Astronautical Society (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Rocket Society (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arbeitsgemeinschaft für Raumfahrtforschung (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bell Aircraft Corporation/Bell Aerosystems Company (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - British Interplanetary Society (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Danish Interplanetary Society (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Forschungsinstitut für Physik der Strahlantriebe (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Astronautical Federation (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Glenn L. Martin Company (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Von Karman Institute for Fluid Dynamics (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wissenschaftliche Gesellschaft für Luft und Raumfahrt (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Misc. international institutional correspondence (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Misc. international institutional correspondence (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Misc. international institutional correspondence (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Misc. international institutional correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series 2. Museum Documents, ca. 1955-1961
  - Museum's official papers, reports (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Museum's official papers, reports (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Museum's official papers, reports (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Museum's official papers, reports (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Museum's official papers, reports (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Museum's official papers, reports (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Museum's official papers, reports (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Report on opening of Gesellschaft für Weltraumforschung (1950) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notes, sketches and ground plan for proposed museum (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Extended memorandum on museum design and purpose (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Information on DGRR library holdings (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Satellite-date collection project of 1958-59 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series 3. Alfred Fritz, personal papers, ca. 1942-1950
  - Alfred Fritz, personal papers (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Alfred Fritz, personal papers (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Alfred Fritz, personal papers (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Alfred Fritz, personal papers, manuscript of Fritz's novel, Urwald (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Alfred Fritz, personal papers, manuscript of Fritz's novel, Urwald (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Series 4. Deutshes Raketen- und Raumfahrt Museum
  - Alfred Fritz, personal papers (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Alfred Fritz, personal papers (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Alfred Fritz, pre-DGRR correspondence, ca. 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Alfred Fritz, pre-DGRR correspondence, ca. 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Alfred Fritz, pre-DGRR correspondence, ca. 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Alfred Fritz, pre-DGRR correspondence, ca. 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Notes/Diagrams/Photographs/correspondence (Box 5)
  - Minor Illustrations (w/ listing) (Box 6)
  - Technical Manuscripts (Radar), class notes and diagrams, ca. 1935-36 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Series 5. Financial Records, ca. 1953-1957
  - DGRR holdings in foreign accounts, 1953-1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - DGRR, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - DGRR, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - DGRR, 1956-57 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - DGRR, 1956-57 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - DGRR, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - DGRR, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Kassenbuch, 1957: "Deutsche Gesellschaft für Raketentechnic und Raumfahrt" (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Kassenbuch, 1955-56: "Gesellschaft für Weltraumforschung E.V. Stuttgart Zuffenhausen" (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, catalogues, and brochures of items selected for the Museum, i.e. bookshelves, storage containers, cameras, etc. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, catalogues, and brochures of items selected for the Museum, i.e. bookshelves, storage containers, cameras, etc. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, catalogues, and brochures of items selected for the Museum, i.e. bookshelves, storage containers, cameras, etc. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, catalogues, and brochures of items selected for the Museum, i.e. bookshelves, storage containers, cameras, etc. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, catalogues, and brochures of items selected for the Museum, i.e. bookshelves, storage containers, cameras, etc. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Series 6. Major Illustrations
  - Blank poster with blue background and large, stylized rocket insignia (insignia of the DGRR) on left side; right side free for entries concerning lectures, events, conferences, etc.; ca. 1955 (Map-case mc)
  - Distance chart concerning trajectory of a moon flight. (Map-case mc)
  - Original drawing on transparent paper of a space suit, as designed by H. Oberth (with attached description); Stuttgart, 1942. (Map-case mc)
  - Three (3) architectural plans in brown print on strong paper, and one (1) frontal-view rendering of the planned museum in Stuttgart; architect Max Benndorf, 1952 (Map-case mc)
  - Two (2) designs on transparent paper of 3-stage rocket and space-station; designed by Wernher von Braun; scale 1:200; Stuttgart, 1969 (Map-case mc)